## **NISHAT ANJUM**

□+8801723124778 | Image: Imag

### Summary\_

I am a committed Software Engineer with a decade of substantial experience in developing and enhancing enterprise-level software solutions. Presently, I hold the position of Principal Software Engineer at an esteemed IT organization in my home country. My proficiency centers around JAVA and JVM-based technology stack, software design patterns, and development methodologies. After a thorough assessment of my substantial professional background and unwavering career aspirations, I am dedicated to embarking on a research-focused Master's Program in Computer Science. I firmly believe that this academic pursuit will pave the way for me to establish a rewarding career as a Computer and Software Specialist in the future.

Education 2

University of Dhaka Dhaka, Bangladesh

BSc. (Honours) in Computer Science and Engineering

2007 - 2011

- CGPA: 3.37/4.00 (German System: 1.9)
- Merit Position: 14<sup>th</sup> out of 45 students
- Total Credit: 148
- Courses: Software Engineering, Data Structures and Algorithms, Computer Programming Language, Database Management System, Operating System, Computer Networks, Data Communication, Discrete Mathematics, Theory of Computation, Artificial Intelligence
- **IELTS**: Overall Band Score **7.5** [L-9, R-7.5, W-7, S-6.5]

### Research Interests

Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning, Database and knowledge-base systems, Data Science and Data Analytics Software Engineering, Application of Machine Learning in Software Engineering

# Academic Research 🗷

#### Title: Throughput Maximization in Device to Device(D2D) Enabled Cellular Network

University Of Dhaka

Supervisor: Professor DR. MD. ABDUR RAZZAQUE

20

In this work, We addressed the spectrum-sharing problem between cellular and underlaying D2D communication. Our main goal was
to maximize the throughput of the underlying 3G cellular network in non-orthogonal Resource-Sharing mode. We proposed a Scheduled
resource-sharing Algorithm for eNodeB that intelligently identified potential D2D connection pairs and optimally shared UpLink and DownLink resources by calculating SINR for each pair.

### Technical Expertise

**Language:** Java, Python, C/C++, JavaScript, TypeScript, R

**Frameworks:** Spring-[Boot, Security, MVC, Webflow, Data JPA, Batch, HATEOAS, GraphQL], Python Flask, Angular, Hibernate, JPA, Mockito

Web Services: REST, SOAP

**Middlewares:** WebLogic, WildFly, Tomcat, TomcatEE, Glassfish

Databases: MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, In-memory Data Structure Store-REDIS, Cloud Object Storage - MINIO

Tools: Maven, Gradle, Ant, Postman, Git, Bitbucket, Docker

OS Platforms: Linux, Windows, Mac

Big Data: Kafka, Apache KUDU, Apache Spark, Apache Druid, Elasticsearch

# Work Experience\_\_\_\_

#### Tiger IT Bangladesh Limited.

Dhaka, Bangladesh Oct 2022 - present

#### **Principal Software Engineer**

• Supervising and training a Development team of four software engineers.

- Providing technical guidance to the team and overseeing the technical aspects of four Government projects and upcoming Projects.
- Regularly attend team meetings to discuss projects, brainstorm ideas, and propose solutions to any issues.

#### **Senior Software Engineer**

Oct 2019 - Sept 2022

- Supervised a team of four software engineers to ascertain the successful completion of deliverables.
- Performed various RnD and provided expert support and guidance on architectural changes in ongoing initiatives taken by the company.
- Continuously contributed to troubleshooting issues in production deployment and performance tuning.
- · Reviewed code for defects and quality against technical documents and standard practices.

Software Engineer Dec 2015 - Sept 2019

- Extensively re-engineered legacy software system to improve scalability and increased performance by approximately 35%.
- Core architect of a large-scale data migration project involving a highly complex process that successfully migrated approximately 120M Demographic and Biometric data within 42 hours.
- Developed High volume and low latency Restful APIs for various client applications serving **responses less than 30ms.**
- Developed data streaming pipeline using Apache Kafka that combine messaging and storage of both historical and real-time data.
- Developed a high-performance real-time fast data Analytics application using Apache Druid, Kudu, and Kafka.
- Designed and developed Report modules for multiple ongoing projects which involved complex query writing.
- · Assisted the Junior Software Engineers in solving technical problems and mentored them in writing high-quality code.

Therap BD Ltd. 🗹 Dhaka, Bangladesh

#### **Associate Software Engineer**

Oct 2014 - Dec 2015

- Worked with Technical Staff to understand problems with software and correct them.
- Developed new features for the **MAR module** of The Therap application.
- Wrote a successful migration script incorporating ETL process to store lookup standard diagnosis codes (e.g. ICD-9/10).
- Solved user reported bugs of different modules in the Therap Application.
- · Learning and experimenting the usability of various technologies in The Therap application.

Junior Software Engineer

Aug 2012 - Sept 2014

- Learning, installing and reviewing various technologies related to software development.
- Investigated users reported bugs in the codebase and resolved them.
- Did code refactoring to increase readability and performance in different modules.

# Industrial Projects 🗷

#### **Bangladesh NID application System**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, Spring Security, JSP, Semactic-UI, JQuery]

· An online public portal where citizen of Bangladesh can apply for NID card and voter registration

#### **Rohingya AFIS And AFRS adjudication System**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Python Flusk, Angular.js, Spring Boot, Ouartz Scheduler]

· An application which ceaselessly verifies new voter applications with Rohingya AFIS and AFRS database

#### **CMS system for Election Commission Officials**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring Boot, Spring Security, JWT Token, JSP, Bootstrap, vue.js]

· Web Application for bangladesh election commission officials to oversee voter registration and NID card applications

#### **Bangladesh Citizen data Migration Project**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring Boot-Scheduling, JDBC, Apache Kafka, Redis]

 A data migration project to migration 120M voter demographic and biometric data to elasticsearch, Apache KUDU, Redis, Minio and Oracle database.

#### **Nepal HSENP Registration System**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, Spring Security, JSP, Semactic UI, JQuery]

· A online public portal where Nepal Citizen can apply for high security embossed number plate for their Vehicles.

#### **Nepal HSENP Application management System**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, Spring Security, Thymeleaf, Bootstrap, JQuery, Oracle database]

• A web application for nepal DOTM officials to supervise HSENP printing applications.

#### Nepal vehicle data migration project

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring-Batch, Spring-Jdbc, Oracle Database]

A data migration projects to migrate 35M vehicle data to Oracle database.

#### **Bangladesh NTMC National Datahub Project**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring Boot, Spring Security, JWT Token, Apache Kafka, Redis, GraphQL]

An ETL project for bangladesh NTMC which accumulate Citizen data from multiple sources and make them accessible for

#### **Vehicle Tracking System - Banngladesh NTMC**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Alient JAVA SDK, MQTT, Caffeine Cache, Spring Boot, Spring Scheduling]

• The application unceasingly accumulates vehicle movement information by interfacing with Alien RFID Reader

### Therap Application

Therap BD Ltd.

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, JSP, EJB, Hibernate JPA, Oracle Database]

- Developed new feature in Medication Administration Record(MAR) module to record patient medication record
- · Developed a migration project to store lookup standard ICD-9/10 diagnosis code into relational Database

# Academic Projects \_\_\_\_\_

#### Buddy Circle-A Social networking web application 🗹

University Of Dhaka

**Internet Programming** 

• An application developed back in 2012 using spring mvc, jsp, html5, jpa, mysql

### Tic Tac Toe Game using ATmega32 microcontroller

University Of Dhaka

Computer Peripherals and Interfacing

2010

2012

• A multiplayer tic-tac-toe game written in C language for ATmega32 Controller

**Dots and Boxes - Online Multiplayer Game** 

Object Oriented Programming-JAVA

• An online multiplayer game developed using JAVA Applet and socket programming

Avoid collision Game

University Of Dhaka

Programming Language Fundamental- C Language

A simple single player game developed using C i-Graphics library

Unix Shell
University Of Dhaka

Operating System

• A simple bash like Unix shell which executed linux command using exec().

### Competition and Achievements \_\_\_\_\_

2015	<b>Runner-Up</b> , Women Table Tennis Tournament arranged by Therap BD. Ltd.	Dhaka, Bangladesh
2007	Education Board Scholarship, HSC Board Exam	Rajshahi, Bangladesh
2005	Education Board Scholarship, SSC Board Exam	Rajshahi, Bangladesh

#### Interests \_\_\_\_\_

**Table Tennis** Table Tennis is my favorite sport of all. I engage in daily table tennis matches with my colleagues.

**Workout** I am passionate about fitness. Some of my favorite activities are western yoga and low-impact aerobics.

Cooking I love baking and Cooking. Baking my birthday cake gives me ultimate joy. I try out new recipes every weekend.

**Traveling** I am an avid traveler. I explore both domestic and international destinations whenever the chance arises.

Music I enjoy almost all types of music. However, primarily I love Soul, Country, Indi, pop, Psychedelic, OST, and K-Pop.

### Languages\_

English Professional proficiency
Bengali Native proficiency
Hindi Bilingual proficiency

University Of Dhaka 2010

2008